Lothar Wolff collection, 1926-1987
George Eastman Museum
- Series 2, Film/TV Projects, 1932-1986
  - Subseries 1,The Earth and Its Peoples, ca. 1932; 1938; 1951-1962; 1967-1986
    - no title (Box C371)
      - List of Unit Sales from The Earth and Its Peoples to Jan. 1965 from 1945 (Folder 16)
        Single page.
      - [Binder labeled "The Earth, Its Peoples"], 1948-1949 (Folder 21)
        Contains location lists, shot lists, and scripts. Inside cover features Wolff's summary of The Earth and Its Peoples as a series of "36 black-and-white short films with a global scope meant to be shown in schools."
  - Subseries 2,Fortress of Peace[aka Vigilant Switzerland], 1964-1966
    - no title (Box C019)
      - [Plaque, "Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences Certificate of Nomination for Award for Fortress of Peace"], 1965
        Wooden plaque announcing the nomination of Fortress of Peace for an Academy Award.
      - [Southern California Motion Picture Council Inc. certificate for Fortress of Peace], 1966 (Folder 2)
        Awarded to Lothar Wolff Productions and the Swiss government.
    - no title (Box C300)
      - [Photo album labeled "Switzerland 63/64"], 1963-1964 (Folder 9)
        Photos taken during the production of Fortress of Peace, aka Vigilant Switzerland. Subjects include Wolff; director John Fernhout; Swiss military personnel; the Swiss Army Pavilion at the 1964 Swiss national exhibition (Expo64). Prints of the same photos appear in album "DI 1963/64," Box 300, Folder 10, in different sizes. Album includes related clippings. In German.
      - [Photo album originally labeled "DI 63/64"], 1963-1964 (Folder 10)
        Photos taken in Switzerland during the production of Fortress of Peace, aka Vigilant Switzerland. Subjects include Wolff; director John Fernhout; Swiss military personnel; the Eiger glacier; the Swiss Army Pavilion at the 1964 Swiss national exhibition (Expo64). Enlargements of many of these photos are found in album labeled "Switzerland 63/64," Box 300, Folder 9. Some photos appear to have been removed from the album. Label missing from album spine.
    - no title (Box C367)
      - Fortress of Peace(1964) Publicity, Screenings etc., 1964-1966 (Folder 24)
        Materials related to Fortress of Peace, [aka Vigilant Switzerland], including newspaper clippings, screening invitations and guest list, the text of a speech delivered at a Swiss Embassy screening, black-and-white publicity photos, and the 38th Annual Academy Awards Presentation program and tickets.
    - no title (Box C368)
      - [Newspaper Clippings, 1951-1966] (Folder 16)
        Clippings regarding Fortress of Peace.
  - Subseries 3,The Joy of Bach, 1967-1985; bulk 1977-1980
    - no title (Box C019)
      - [Framed The Joy of Bach ad], ca. 1980
        Color advertisement.
    - no title (Box C301)
      - Christopher Nupen(Allegro Films), 1977 (Folder 1)
        Correspondence concerning The Joy of Bach; Allegro Films catalog, production notes.
      - Material on the Brooklyn Boys Chorus, 1976-1979 (Folder 11)
        Programs, clippings, press materials.
      - DDR-E. German TV; Correspondence, 1977-1978; 1984-1985 (Folder 13)
        Correspondence, including telexes, between Wolff and Fernsehen der DDR regarding the production of The Joy of Bach, mostly in German.
      - Richard C. Kestler,M.L. Byers, Inc. Concert Management, 1978 (Folder 35)
        Letter from Kestler to Wolff regarding Swingle II and The Joy of Bach.
      - Roy E. Larsen, April 24, 1976 (Folder 38)
      - Teo Morca(Dancer), 1979-1983 (Folder 50)
        Promotional materials, press releases, newspaper reviews and clippings regarding Teodoro Morca, a flamenco dancer with Bach in his repertoire. Correspondence with Wolff concerning possible film project.
      - Sigaar, Jacqueline(Paris), 1977; 1983 (Folder 68)
        Correspondence regarding ballooning project, UNESCO concert film [in French],The Joy of Bach.
      - Nils C. Nilson,Taurus-Film, Munich, ca. 1979 (Folder 71)
        Correspondence regarding TV licensing of The Joy of Bach; project proposals.
      - Victor Vicas, 1979 (Folder 78)
        Correspondence regarding Bach project.
    - no title (Box 307)
      - The Joy of Bach-- Ninety Minute Television Program for Lutheran Film Associates by Allan Sloane, 1978 (Folder 2)
        Script by Allan Sloane.
      - The Joy of Bach-- Exports from Trip to Europe, 1977-1978 (Folder 4)
        Notes, contact information, receipts, brochures, stamps from DDR and UK, correspondence.
      - Material on Bach, 1959; 1978 (Folder 5)
        Sheet music, newspaper articles, pamphlets, programs and flyers related to Bach.
      - European Distribution of The Joy of Bach, 1978-1980 (Folder 6)
        Correspondence, mostly in German, some with English translation.
      - The Joy of Bach-- Brochures of Studio Hamburg-- Price List, 1978 (Folder 7)
        Brochures regarding the studio, equipment, and location [in English], price list and music [in German].
      - Contracts with GDR Television and Production Bills, 1978 (Folder 8)
        In English and German, with some English translation.
      - Letters Concerning Manfred Schnelle, dancer (The Joy of Bach), 1967; 1974; 1978-1979 (Folder 9)
        Correspondence, flyers, and programs [in German].
      - Correspondence with GDR Television, 1979-1982; 1984 (Folder 10)
        Flyer, booklet of GDR Television productions, programming list [in German and English].
      - Dr. Hans Gruß[Gruiss?] -- Conductor GDR, 1977-1978 (Folder 11)
        Programs from Karl-Marx-Universitat Leipzig[in German and English].
      - Letter by Curtis W. Davis, 1977 (Folder 12)
        Letter
      - Correspondence with March Five, Inc., 1978 (Folder 13)
        Overview of the film, press release.
      - Cast List GDR Actors, 1977-1978 (Folder 14)
        Casting suggestions, headshots, program, and clippings.
      - Correspondence with Centre Georges Pompidou, 1977-1978 (Folder 15)
        Correspondence in French and English.
      - Correspondence with Dirk Duewel,Studio Hamburg, 1978 (Folder 16)
        Correspondence in German and English.
      - Notes to Morrie Roizman, Editor of The Joy of Bach, 1978-1979; 1983 (Folder 17)
        Correspondence and production materials, including a shortened version of the script. Materials in English and German.
      - Correspondence with Brian Blessed, 1978-1979 (Folder 18)
        Correspondence, Actor’s in Television Motion Picture Minimum Three-Day Contract, CTVC new studio facilities pamphlet, notes and addresses, Fenton House Appeal pamphlet.
      - GDR -- Stock Footage Screenings, 1975; 1977 (Folder 19)
        Stock Footage Screening Reports, mostly in English with German, French, and/or Russian translations.
      - Jomsborg Prod Inc., Bills, 1977-1978 (Folder 20)
        Includes border crossing documentation for cinematographer Erich Kollmar.
      - Bach Festival Leipzig, 1975; 1977-1978 (Folder 21)
        Correspondence, articles, postcards, pamphlets, programs, and notes. Materials in German and English. Some letters include translations.
      - Bonded Services -- Stored Originals, 1978 (Folder 22)
        Lists of film elements stored at Bonded Services; film storage receipts.
      - Production Orders, 1978-1979 (Folder 23)
        Production orders, price list, correspondence with companies and organizations involved in the production of The Joy of Bach(United Nations Film Library,Lutheran Film Associates, sound and other equipment rentals).
      - Newspaper articles, notes, programs The Joy of Bach, 1977-1979 (Folder 24)
        Research and related materials.
      - Newspaper articles, programs, notes, 1977-1980 (Folder 25)
        Joy of Bach-related materials. Also includes a list of PBS station airtimes, postcards, transcript of an interview with Brian Blessed by Robert E. A. Lee.
      - Music, 1979 (Folder 26)
        Music cue sheets, memos, cast lists, dialogue-narration script for The Joy of Bach.
      - 60 Minute Version, 1979 (Folder 27)
        Cuts considered for a 60-minute version of The Joy of Bach.
      - WQED Pittsburgh -- Promotion, 1979 (Folder 28)
        List of artists who might contribute to the promotion of The Joy of Bach.
      - Reactions, 1978-1979 (Folder 29)
        Reactions to The Joy of Bach, including a mass-media newsletter,Booklist review/promotion, comments/congratulations on the film.
      - Screening, 1978-1979 (Folder 30)
        Flyers and guest list for a screening of The Joy of Bach.
      - [Untitled], 1979-1980 (Folder 31)
        List of film elements at Bonded Services and Magno Sound, with an inventory of negative cuts; correspondence listing film materials at Lab Pictures; notes for 60-minute and 85-minute versions of The Joy of Bach.
      - Domestic Distribution, 1978-1979 (Folder 32)
        Information regarding the domestic distribution of The Joy of Bach.
      - "Flying J.S.B. in the G.D.R." by Lothar Wolff, 1978 (Folder 33)
        Drafts, with the "next-to-last" draft dated 1978.
      - News Releases concerning The Joy of Bach by Lutheran Film Associates, 1977-1978 (Folder 34)
      - Correspondence with Lutheran Film Associates concerning The Joy of Bach, 1977-1978 (Folder 35)
        Correspondence, including proposal to The George Gund Foundation.
      - Lutheran Film Associates Meeting, April, 1978 (Folder 36)
      - Wash. D.C.Lutheran Resources Commission--The Joy of Bach, 1977-1978 (Folder 37)
        Correspondence in English and German, with English translations.
      - Sequence List for The Joy of Bach, ca. 1979 (Folder 38)
        Sequence list.
      - Miscellaneous Letters Concerning The Joy of Bach, 1979-1980 (Folder 39)
        Correspondence includes postcards and cost estimate for lab work.
      - [The Joy of Bach script drafts], 1977-1978 (Folder 40)
        Black hard-cover binder containing drafts and revisions, with notations.
      - [Unlabeled binder containing "The Joy of Bach: Cue Sheet and Dialogue-Narration Script"], 1978 (Folder 41)
        Includes Klaus Genderies business card, notes.
      - [Binder labeled "The Joy of Bach: A Ninety Minute Television Program for Lutheran Film Associates" by Allan Sloane], 1978 (Folder 42)
        Red binder containing Sloane's script. Label on cover reads "Morrie Roizman."
      - [Booklet titled "Everyman’s Bach: A TV Special for Christmas 1976"], 1975 (Folder 43)
      - [Booklet titled "The Current Popularity of Bach"], ca. 1975 (Folder 44)
    - no title (Box Box C308)
      - Lutheran Film Associates-- Meetings -- Reports, 1978-1979 (Folder 1)
      - Lutheran Film Associates-- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1974-1979 (Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence Concerning The Joy of Bach, 1981 (Folder 7)
        Correspondence [in English, French, German]. Includes letter from "Allan" to Thomas McDermott regarding Howard Hughes film project; production assistant resume; press materials regarding PRIMOB (Projected Image Mobile) slide projection in 3 dimensions;Erwin Leiser bio; German magazine article regarding Bernice Abbott by Leiser.
      - Announcement of "Prize of the Public" in Besançon, France for the The Joy of Bach, 1981 (Folder 8)
        Memo announcing award.
      - The Joy of Bach, ca. 1979 (Folder 9)
        Photograph contact sheets for The Joy of Bach, including production, location shots; landscape with tracing paper; 2 8x10 black-and-white negatives for radio station KFAC's "Bachanalia" ad; 8x10 black-and-white photo of Robert Deutsch,Rosalyn Tureck and the Moog synthesizer.
      - Manfred Schnelle DDR Choreog., 1978 (Folder 10)
        Two black-and-white photographs of dancer/choreographer Manfred Schnelle in performance.
      - St. Thomas Kirche Leipzig, 1977 (Folder 11)
        Two black-and-white photographs of the gate at St. Thomas Church in Leipzig.
      - no title, The Joy of Bach DDR -- Location; 1978 (Folder 12)
        Color photographs, including interior/exterior shots taken at the Neue Palais, Potsdam.
      - [Binder labeled "The Joy of Bach 77/78 Vol. 1 12" on spine], 1977-1978 (Folder 24)
        Yellow 3-ring loose-leaf binder with magnetic pages containing black-and-white and color photographs of The Joy of Bach-related personnel and locations.
      - [Binder labeled "The Joy of Bach’78 Vol. 2 13"], 1978 (Folder 25)
        Three-ring plastic Time magazine binder with magnetic pages containing black-and-white and color photos of The Joy of Bach-related personnel and locations, including Wolff,Brian Blessed,Robert E. A. Lee.
      - [Binder labeled "The Joy of Bach Vol. 3 14"], ca. 1978 (Folder 26)
        Three-ring plastic Time magazine binder with magnetic pages containing black-and-white and color photographs of The Joy of Bach-related personnel and locations.
    - no title (Box C019A)
      - [Plaque for The Joy of Bach, U.S. Industrial Film Festival], 1982
        First Place, Gold Camera Award presented to Lothar Wolff.
      - [Plaque, awarded by Lutheran Brotherhood for The Joy of Bach], 1980
        Presented to Lothar Wolff on September 24, 1980.
    - no title (Box Box C367)
      - Stickers: "The Bach Stops Here,", undated (Folder 36)
        3 WQED FM bumper stickers.
    - no title (Box OS-1)
      - ["Bachanalia" advertisement], undated (Folder 8)
        Photo reproduction of ad for radio station KFAC's "Bachanalia."
    - no title (Box OS-2)
      - [Envelope labeled "Bach Artwork – Cataloged 4-28-87 UA"], ca. 1979 (Folder 7)
        Envelope contains folder made of two large sheets of board inscribed “Top: Included are 2 Worksheets of Camera Instructions, 3 Backgrounds, 15 Cels – Please open with caution.” Cels and paintings depict stars and galaxies; cels are likely those used in The Joy of Bach. Materials were removed from envelope and folder in August, 2015.
      - [Framed CINE 1980 certificate awarded to The Joy of Bach] (Folder 8)
        "Golden Eagle" certificate awarded by the Council on International Nontheatrical Events(CINE).
  - Subseries 4,Lost Boundaries, 1949
    - no title (Box C368)
      - Script for "Lost Boundaries" -- A Louis de Rochemont Production, 1949 (Folder 2)
        Script
  - Subseries 5,The March of Time, 1933; 1936-1951; 1957; 1969-1970; 1975; 1979-1982
    - no title (Box C301)
      - Pete Hopkinson:"The Screen of Change" planned book, 1978-1979 (Folder 27)
    - no title (Box C309)
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence Concerning the March of Time, 1936; 1942-1948; 1969-1970; 1980; 1982 (Folder 1)
        Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, newsletters; Wolff's permit to leave the US; discussion of Time’s "road back" peacetime strategy. Materials in English, French, and German.
      - Photos taken during March of Time filming, 1938; 1941; undated (Folder 3)
        Mostly undated. Some photos dated 1938 and 1941.
      - The March of Time-- Subject Index, ca. 1951 (Folder 5)
        List of subjects covered by The March of Time series. Document is undated but the last subject entry is from 1951.
      - The March of Time Revisited -- Proposals, 1975 (Folder 7)
        Bound proposal, newspaper articles,The Best of March of Time, correspondence with Time-Life Films and Lurco Films Inc., subject list.
      - T/L Archives --March of Time, 1981 (Folder 9)
        Correspondence with Time, Inc. regarding The March of Time.
      - Prof. Reischauer "…and then Japan"March of Time, 1984 (Folder 11)
        Photocopy of March of Time issue "… And Then Japan" shot list; interview questions for Harvard professor Edwin O. Reischauer. The date 1984 appears on the folder in Wolff's hand, though the actual documents are undated.
      - [Three-ring loose-leaf binder labeled "March of Time I"], 1933-1948; 1979 (Folder 20)
      - [Three-ring loose-leaf binder labeled "March of Time II"], 1936; 1940-1943 (Folder 21)
    - [Album labeled "Denmark 1934/36 and 1939"], 1934-1940; 1982 (Folder 7)
      Photo captioned "Shooting for March of Time."
    - no title (Box C367)
      - Speech Made by Lothar Wolff (?) at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on March of Time, 1957 (Folder 15)
        Text of 1957 MoMA speech, with corrections and notes.
      - Newspaper Clippings for Ramparts We Watch, 1940 (Folder 23)
        A March of Time feature production.Variety review; newspaper clipping; photo of Louis de Rochemont, Lothar Wolff, and Thomas Orchard.
  - Subseries 6, Marshall Plan Films, 1951; 1979
    - no title (Box C367)
      - Marshall Plan Films, 1979 (Folder 25)
        Correspondence regarding research and proposed screenings of the Marshall Plan Films at the Nyon Festival; index to "Catalogue of Documentary Films ECA" [list of Economic Cooperation Administration films].
      - An Evening of Marshall Plan Films,MoMA, 1951 (Folder 26)
        Typed program draft with introduction.
  - Subseries 7,Martin Luther, 1952-1954; 1971; 1978; 1983
    - no title (Box Box C019)
      - [CINE 1971 certificate for Martin Luther Excerpt] (Folder 3)
        Certificate congratulating Wolff.
    - no title (Box Box C308)
      - Miscellaneous on Martin Luther, 1953-1954 (Folder 19)
        Ads, articles [in English, German], including an article for the New Hampshire Churchman written by Wolff.
      - Annual Academy Awards, Nominations,Martin Luther, 1954 (Folder 20)
        "Twenty-Sixth Annual Academy Awards Presentation" program.
      - Lutheran Film Associates-- News Release for Martin Luther, 1954 (Folder 21)
      - [Martin Luther script], ca. 1953 (Folder 23)
        Undated 234-page screenplay, paper cover detached.
      - [Binder labeled "Martin Luther 52/54 7"], 1952-1954; 1978 (Folder 27)
        Black 3-ring loose-leaf binder/scrapbook containing newspaper clippings regarding production of Martin Luther[in English, German], ads;Martin Luther ad slick; press release concerning the banning of the film in Quebec; 1978 Louis de Rochemont obituary.
    - no title (Box C352C)
      - [Screen Writers’ Guild Nomination for Award for Martin Luther], ca. 1953
        Nomination for best written drama of 1953. Framed certificate.
    - no title (Box Box C356)
      - [Photo album, "Zur Erinnerung an den Film Martin Luther Mr. Lothar Wolff herzlichst gewidmet, Wiesbaden August-October 1952"] (Folder 1)
        ["Commemorating the film Martin Luther, Mr. Lothar Wolff, sincerely dedicated, Wiesbaden August-October 1952] Commemorative album of black-and-white photographs taken during the production of Martin Luther. Album is likely the first of a three-volume commemorative set. See Box C356, Folders 2 and 3.
      - [Photo album, "Martin Luther Vol. II, 1952"], 1953 (Folder 2)
        Album of small black-and-white stills from Martin Luther. Invitation from Louis de Rochemont Associates to a preview screening of Martin Luther at the Museum of Modern Art on March 12th, 1953, and note "Property of Lothar Wolff." Album is likely the second of a three-volume commemorative set. See Box C356, Folders 1 and 3.
      - [Photo album, "Martin Luther Vol. III 1952"] (Folder 3)
        Album of small black-and-white stills from Martin Luther. Album is likely the third of a three-volume commemorative set. See Box C356, Folders 1 and 2.
    - no title (Box Box C368)
      - Introduction for Martin Luther(1953) by David Soul in 1983 and script from Martin Luther (Folder 13)
        An introduction and coda for a rebroadcast of the 1953 film [recut to 83 mins]; script.
  - Subseries 8, National Geographic Society Films [General], 1973-1983
    - no title (Box C301)
      - Telepool/Hemmings, 1976 (Folder 73)
        Correspondence regarding proposed National Geographic series "Look at the World" (working title) using adaptations of Telepool productions;Crossing the Himalayas synopsis; film lab processing price list; materials related to Videomarketing Ltd. releases
    - no title (Box C355)
      - Correspondence with Hermann Schlenker-- Dokumentarfilm, 1973-1976 (Folder 25)
        Correspondence [in German, English] regarding German ethnographic filmmaker Hermann Schlenker’s work, some with Wolff’s screening reports attached.
      - TELECIP& National Geographic Society, 1976 (Folder 26)
        Correspondence with TELECIP (Compagnie Internationale de Programmes de Télévision) regarding Worlds of Life and other films for possible adaptation.
      - National Geographic Society -- Switzerland, 1974-1976 (Folder 27)
        Correspondence with Telepool[Zurich, Switzerland] regarding ethnographic films for possible National Geographic Society TV adaptations, with attached descriptions of Telepool films [in German, English];Geology of the Alps series segment "Fossil Coral Reefs in the Alps" script, segment outlines and related correspondence;Heritage de l’Homme series segments "Turquie I & II" scripts.
      - Payments, Bills from National Geographic Society, 1979-1981 (Folder 28)
        Bills, stubs, expense reports, receipts, and other expenditure records related to production of The Moon,The Sun, and Our Solar System; Du Art Film Laboratories price list; production/post-production invoices, including invoice from composer Gerhard Trede.
      - Budgets -- National Geographic Society, 1979 (Folder 29)
        Correspondence, budgets, and notes regarding production of "the solar films" [three planned films about the sun: "The Sun and Solar Radiation," "The Solar Furnace," and "Our Solar System"] and other projects; "World War II: GI Diary" line-item budget; "The People of Asia" TV series preliminary cost estimate per subject.
      - Screening Reports for NGS in Hamburg, 1976 (Folder 31)
        List of films selected for screening in Hamburg; synopses of films produced by Polytel International GmbH, Hamburg; Polytel correspondence; Hamburg screening reports, most with synopses attached; titles of films screened in Hamburg listed as "Acceptable," "Possible" and "N.G."
      - Screenings for National Geographic Society in London, 1974-1975 (Folder 32)
        Lists of films selected for screening in London as potential Other People Other Places III segments; screening reports, many with synopses attached; related correspondence.
      - Screening for National Geographic Society, 1976; 1983 (Folder 33)
        Shot lists for "Lazi -- Safari Film," "Kenya Footage" and other stock footage; lists of still and stock footage, including footage of the Macy’s Thanksgiving Day Parade balloons; stock footage purchase order; notes on "Rigid Airships" and "Airship Industries" films; 1976 screening reports for "Bali, Island of the Gods," "The Solomon Islanders," "The Way of the Sword."
      - Letters to Dennis Kane, 1975-1977; 1982-1983 (Folder 34)
        Correspondence with National Geographic Society Chief of Television Division Dennis B. Kane and others regarding Wolff’s consultancy and several film projects including The World We Live In,Man and Animal, and an adaptation of the 26-episode Australian series Faces of Change for syndication. Also included are screening reports, list of potential members of a cable television "Geographic Cable Alliance," paystubs and newspaper clippings.
      - Sidney Platt, Manager, Educational Films,National Geographic Society, 1979-1981 (Folder 35)
        Correspondence with educators, scientists, film producers and others regarding the development of solar system films;National Geographic index pages [photocopies] with notations; educational-film promotional material; memo/report from market research: K-12 Filmstrip Title Survey results.
      - [Tax Exemption Certification], undated (Folder 37)
        Tax Exempt Organization Certification documents. Folder was originally titled "Resale Certificates.
      - [Red 3-ring binder with tape label on spine "Paris, Munich, Hamburg/NGS/Kane Jan. Feb. 76"], 1976 (Folder 41)